MATTHEW BATTLEY

PhD Student, University of Warwick

@ matbatt@gmail.com

J +44-7490-577663

Geneva, Switzerland

✓ Observatoire de Genève, 51b Chemin Pegasi, 1290 Versoix, Switzerland





RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Postdoctoral Researcher

Geneva Observatory, University of Geneva

Oct 2022 - Present

Geneva, Switzerland

• Supervisor: Assistant Professor Monika Lendl

• Research:

The discovery and characterisation of exoplanets, primarily focused on young and active systems. Projects include the continued search for new young exoplanets in photometry, spectroscopic follow-up of young exoplanet candidates, full system analyses for a long-period exoplanet and young low-mass eclipsing binary, ephemeris maintenance and stellar activity analyses. This research frequently makes use of Python coding, photometric, spectroscopic and statistical analyses, database manipulation, and exoplanet/stellar activity modelling. It utilises a wide range of data from TESS, Kepler/K2, NGTS, Gaia, Coralie and HARPS.

PhD Student

Department of Physics, University of Warwick

Oct 2018 - Present

Coventry, United Kingdom

- Supervisor: Professor Don Pollacco
- Funding: Chancellor's International Scholarship (Warwick)
- Thesis: "Tracing exoplanets through time with TESS". This research primarily focused on searching for new planets around young (<1Gyr) active stars in photometric data. This included the design of young-star-specific detrending methods for photometric data and analysis/searches through a range of data sources such as Gaia, TESS, Kepler and NGTS, alongside utilising machine-learning based techniques to classify, understand and detrend challenging stellar activity.

Research Assistant

Centre for Advanced Composite Materials, University of Auckland

i Jan 2018 - June 2018

Auckland, New Zealand

Responsibilities:

• Thermo-mechanical modelling, analysis and testing of two novel wireless charging systems in development at CACM, in collaboration with a large overseas company.

Summer Research Student

Centre for Advanced Composite Materials, University of Auckland

Dec 2016 - Feb 2017

Auckland, New Zealand

Responsibilities:

• Design and analysis of a novel small-scale inductive power transfer system. This included numerical modelling of the coupled thermal and electromagnetic physics of the system, prototype design and laboratory testing

RESEARCH OVERVIEW

I am a Postdoctoral Researcher at Geneva Observatory (University of Geneva), supervised by Assistant Professor Monika Lendl. My main research focus is the discovery and characterisation of exoplanets around young stars. I have extensive experience with Python coding, analysis of photometric and spectroscopic data, exoplanet modelling and stellar activity analysis, alongside experience in machine learning and vetting of exoplanet candidates. I also have significant experience writing telescope proposals, having been both a PI and Co-I on numerous proposals for TESS, JWST, OPTICON and ESO telescopes.

Alongside my PhD in astrophysics, I also hold a mechanical engineering degree with a wide range of experience in the design, modelling, manufacturing and testing of complex systems, including rocket components and inductive charging technology.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. in Astrophysics University of Warwick, UK

October 2018 - September 2022

Supervisor: Prof Don Pollacco

Project: Tracing exoplanets through time

with TESS

BE(Hons)/BSc in Mechanical Engineering/Physics

University of Auckland, NZ

March 2013 - November 2017

Grade: 1st Class Honours

Specialisations: Astrophysics, mechanical

and thermal design, geophysics

Schooling

Mount Albert Grammar School, NZ

a Jan 2008 - Dec 2012

NZQA Scholarships in Physics, Calculus,

Statistics and English

NCEA Level 3 with Excellence

NCEA Level 2 with Excellence

NCEA Level 1 with Excellence

Subjects: Physics, Calculus, Statistics, Chem-

istry, English, History



Student Intern

Fisher & Paykel Healthcare Ltd

Dec 2015 - Feb 2016

Auckland, New Zealand

Responsibilities:

- Detailed design and development of a small scale humidification prototype for use in CPAP therapy
- Testing and communication of results verbally/through reports
- Significant use of Computer Aided Design software
- Investigation into novel alternate materials

Propulsion Intern

Rocket Lab Ltd

Dec 2013 - Feb 2015

Auckland, New Zealand

Two related 3-month internships:

- December 2013 February 2014: Design, manufacture and initial testing of a miniature turbopump, part of the rocket propulsion system
- **December 2014 February 2015**: Continued pump development, optimization of rocket trajectories and compiling a report for a specific rocket configuration

Responsibilities:

- Understanding physics of turbopump operation and developing design calculations for simple and complex designs
- Establishing and developing design layouts for a centrifugal pump
- Considerable Computer Aided Design for complex geometries
- Communicating with manufacturers to obtain specific pieces
- · Prototype testing to specification and endurance
- Report writing and communication of results

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Lab Demonstrator University of Warwick

Oct 2018 - Oct 2021

Coventry, United Kingdom

Responsibilities:

- Guiding independent learning of second-year undergraduate physics students through hands-on laboratories
- Explaining new techniques, concepts and the use of specialist equipment
- Answering questions from students where extra explanation or further extension is required

Private Tutor

Ardent Education

March 2013 - July 2018

Auckland, New Zealand

Responsibilities:

- Tutoring Secondary School and undergraduate University of Auckland students in mathematics, physics, statistics and general engineering
- Planning lessons, explaining concepts to develop their understanding and setting problems
- Communicating with the students to establish critical points to focus on

COMPUTING

Python Matlab C++ (basic)

Microsoft Office ETEX Libre Office

Solidworks Creo Parametric ANSYS

ABAQUS FEA TOPCAT

AWARDS

T

Chancellor's International Scholarship (2018)

Awarded to the most outstanding incoming international PhD students at the University of Warwick



Heavy Engineering Research Association Prize (2016)

Awarded for the best final year project in Mechanical Engineering



First in Course Awards (2014/2016/2017)

Awarded to the top student in Physics 213, Physics 330 and MECHENG 700 at the University of Auckland

SKILLS

Excellent written/spoken communication

Eye for detail Multidisciplinary knowledge

Hard-working Persistent Committed

Driven Adaptable Leadership Qualities

Conscientious worker alone and in teams

OBSERVING

Observatoire de Haute-Provence (OHP) SOPHIE echelle spectrograph | 13 nights Observing as part of the SOPHIE timeshare, primarily on the search for circumbinary planets.

ESO La Silla Observatory (remote)

CORALIE spectrograph; EulerCAM | 12 nights Spectroscopic and photometric observations for Geneva's ongoing timeshare programs on the 1.2m Leonhard Euler telescope, including my own program on following up young transiting exoplanet candidates.

Upcoming:

ESO La Silla Observatory (remote)
HARPS/NIRPS spectrographs | 9 nights
Observer for Geneva programs on HARPS/NIRPS
spectrographs on the la Silla 3.6m telescope
for the P112 observation period.

SCIENTIFIC PRESENTATIONS

Talks & Seminars

2022 | "Tracing sxoplanets through time with TESS"

Geneva exoplanet seminar, Geneva Observatory, Switzerland

2021 | "Revisiting the Kepler Field with TESS"

TESS Science Conference 2, MIT, USA

2021 | Tracking Exoplanets through Time with TESS"

UK Exoplanet Community Meeting, University of Birmingham, UK 2021 | "The Curious Case of Young Exoplanets: Unlocking the secrets of young exoplanets with multi-instrument observations"

StScI Summer Symposium, STScI, USA

2019 | "Fantastic Planets and How to Find Them"

ACORNS, University of Warwick, UK

2019 | "The Curious Case of Exoplanet Teenagers"

Warwick AstroSoc Symposium, University of Warwick, UK

Poster Presentations

2021 | "The YOUNGSTER Program: Extending the search for young transiting exoplanets"

"Circumstellar Disks and Young Planets", 2021 Sagan Exoplanet Summer Workshop, California Institute of Technology, USA 2020 | "A search for Young Exoplanets in the S1-5 TESS FFIs" Exoplanets III, University of Heidelberg, Germany 2020 | "Searching for Young Exoplanets with TESS" "Extreme Precision Radial Velocity", 2020 Sagan Exoplanet Summer Workshop, California Institute of Technology, USA 2019 | "Searching for Young Planets with TESS"

PLATO Science Meeting 2019, University of Warwick, UK

PUBLICATIONS

First-author journal articles

Three published + two additional papers in prep.

YOUNG Star detrending for Transiting Exoplanet Recovery (YOUNG-STER) – II. Using self-organizing maps to explore young star variability in sectors 1–13 of TESS data

Battley, M.P., Armstrong, D.J & Pollacco, D. (2022), MNRAS, 511, 3 Revisiting the Kepler field with TESS: Improved ephemerides using TESS 2min data

Battley, M.P., et al., (2021), MNRAS, 503, 2

A search for young exoplanets in Sectors 1-5 of the TESS full-frame images

Battley, M.P., Pollacco, D. & Armstrong, D.J. (2020), MNRAS, 496, 2

Co-authored journal articles

12 published articles as co-author, including:

Early Release Science of the exoplanet WASP-39b with JWST NIR-Cam

Ahrer, E.-M. et al. (2023), Nature, 614, 7949

Periodic stellar variability from almost a million NGTS light curves Briegal, J.T. et al. (2022), MNRAS, 513, 1

A Mini-Neptune from TESS and CHEOPS Around the 120 Myr Old AB Dor Member HIP 94235

Zhou, G. et al. (2022), AJ, 163, 6

BEBOP III. Observations and an independent mass measurement of Kepler-16 (AB) b - the first circumbinary planet detected with radial velocities

Triaud, A.H.M.J. et al. (2022), MNRAS, 511, 3

HD 213885b: a transiting 1-d-period super-Earth with an Earth-like composition around a bright (V = 7.9) star unveiled by TESS Espinoza, N. et al. (2020) MNRAS, 491, 2

OUTREACH

2023 | Fantasy Basel

Exhibitor for Planet-S (Swiss exoplanet/planetary science consortium), providing public demonstrations and planetarium shows for the general public.

2022 - 2023 | **Observatoire de Genève** Outreach tours of the observatory for both

visiting schools and the general public, as well as planetarium shows for open days.

2020 | Warwick Knowledge Centre

Composed a brief public outreach article for the online University of Warwick Knowledge Centre entitled "Myths and Legends of the Pleiades"

2018 - 2022 | Planetarium

Visited a number of different primary schools in the local area with the inflatable Warwick planetarium to show children presentations about the hunt for exoplanets and alien life. Also attended public Q&A sessions at these schools.

CLUBS/SOCIETIES

2019 - 2022 | Warwick Mountaineering and Hiking Club

Treasurer; Captain; Vice-President
Two years on the executive committee for
the hiking club at the University of Warwick,
including handling the club's finances, organising weekly fitness events and training the
next generation of club members in hiking
and mountaineering skills.

2013-2018 | Auckland University Tramping Club

Safety Officer, Captain, Vice-President
Six years of significant involvement with the local tramping (hiking) club at the University of Auckland NZ, completing everything from training new members in outdoor skills, organising hikes and transport, leading the club in the Club Captain role and handling the safety of the club as a whole.